BUILDING After another week of rain the high arch of blue sky appeared again and
the sun which poured down was quite hot.
Though there had been no chance to see either the secret garden or dick
Mistress Mary had enjoyed herself very much. The week had not seemed
long. She had spent hours of every day with Colin in his room, talking about
rajas or gardens or Dickon and the cottage on the mo They had looked at the splendid books
and pictures and sometimes Mary had read things to Colin, and sometimes he had
read a little to her. When he was amused and interested she thought he scarcely
looked like an invalid at all, except that his face was so colorless and he
was always on the sofa. "You are a sly young one to listen
and get out of your bed to go following things up like you did that night," Mrs.
Medlock said once. "But there's no saying it's not been
a sort of blessing to the lot of us. He's
not had a tantrum or a whining fit since you made friends. The nurse was just
going to give up the case because she was so sick of him,
but she says she doesn't mind staying now you've gone on duty with her," laughing a
little. In her talks with Colin, Mary had tried to be very cautious about the
secret garden. There were certain things she wanted to find out from him, but she
felt that she must find them out without asking him direct questions. In the first place, as she
began to like to be with him, she wanted to discover whether he was the kind of
of boy you could tell a secret to. He was
not in the least like Dickon, but he was evidently so pleased with the idea of a
garden no one knew anything about that she thought perhaps he could be
trusted. But she had not known him long enough to be
sure. The second thing she wanted to find out was
this: If he could be trusted— —if he really could— —wouldn't it be possible to take
him to the garden without having anyone find find it out? The grand doctor had said that he
must have fresh air and Colin had said that he would not mind fresh air in a secret
garden. Perhaps if he had a great deal of fresh air and knew Dickon and the robin
and saw things growing he might not think so much about
dying. Mary had seen herself in the glass sometimes lately when she had realized
that she looked quite a different creature from the child she had seen
when she ared arrived from India. This child looked nicer. Even Martha had seen a change in
her the air from the Moore has done thee good already," she had said th not nigh so
yell and th not nigh so scrawny. Even th hair doesn't slamp down on their head so
flat. It's got some life in it so as it sticks out a
bit." "It's like me," said Mary. "It's growing stronger and fatter. I'm sure there's
more of it." "It looks it, for sure," said Martha, ruffling it up a little around
her face th not half so ugly when it's that way and there's a bit of red in
their cheeks." If gardens and fresh air had been good for her perhaps they would be good
for Colin. But then, if he hated people to look at him, perhaps he would not like to
see Dickon. "Why does it make you angry when you are looked at?" she inquired one day.
"I always hated it," he answered, "even when I was very little. Then when they took me
to the seaside and I used to lie in my carriage everybody used to stare and
ladies would stop and talk to my nurse and then they would begin to whisper and
I knew then they were saying I shouldn't live to grow up. Then sometimes the
ladies would pat my cheeks and say 'Poor child!' Once when a lady did that I I
screamed out loud and bit her hand. She was so frightened she ran
away." "She thought you had gone mad like a dog," said Mary, not at all
admiringly. "I don't care what she thought," said Colin,
frowning. "I wonder why you didn't scream and bite me when I came into your room?"
said Mary. Then she began to smile slowly.
"I thought you were a ghost or a dream," he
said. "You can't bite a ghost or a dream, and if you scream they don't care." "Would
you hate it if— —if a boy looked at you?"
Mary asked uncertainly. He lay back on his cushion and paused
thoughtfully. "There's one boy," he said quite slowly, as if he were thinking over
every word, "there's one boy I believe I shouldn't mind. It's that boy who knows where the
foxes live— —Dickon." "I'm sure you wouldn't mind him," said Mary.
"The birds don't and other animals," he said, still thinking it over, "perhaps
that's why I shouldn't. He's a sort of animal charmer and I am a boy animal."
Then he laughed and she laughed too; in fact it ended in there both laughing a
great deal and finding the idea of a boy animal hiding in his hole very funny
indeed. What Mary felt afterward was that she need not fear about Dicken
On that first morning when the sky was blue again Mary wakened very early. The
sun was pouring in slanting rays through the blinds and there was something so
joyous in the sight of it that she jumped out of bed and ran to the window.
She drew up the blinds and opened the window itself and a great waft of fresh,
scented air blew in upon her. The mo was blue and the whole world looked as if
something Magic had happened to it. There were tender little floating sounds here
and there and everywhere, as if scores of birds were beginning to tune up for a
concert. Mary put her hand out of the window and held it in the sun. "It's warm—
—warm!" she said. "It will make the green points push up and up and up, and it will
make the bulbs and roots work and struggle with all their might under the
earth." She kneeled down and leaned out of the window as far far as she could,
breathing big breaths and sniffing the air until she laughed because she
remembered what dickens's mother had said about the end of his nose quivering like a
rabbits It must be very early," she said.
"The little clouds are all pink and I've never seen the sky look like this. No one
is up. I don't even hear the stable boys."
A sudden thought made her scramble to her feet. "I can't wait! I am going to see
the garden!"
She had learned to dress herself by this time and she put on her clothes in 5
minutes. She knew a small side door which she could unbolt herself and she flew
downstairs in her stocking feet and put on her shoes in the hall. She unchained
and unbolted and unlocked and when the door was open she sprang across the step
with one bound, and there she was standing on the grass, which seemed to
have turned green, and with the sun pouring down on her and warm sweet wafts
about her and the fluting and twittering and singing coming from every bush and
tree. She clasped her hands for pure joy and looked up in the sky and it was so
blue and pink and pearly and white and flooded with springtime light that she
felt as if she must flute and sing aloud herself and knew that thrushes and
robins and skylars could not possibly help it. She ran around the shrubs and paths
toward the secret garden. "It is all different already," she
said. "The grass is greener and things are sticking up everywhere and things are
uncurling and green buds of leaves are showing. This afternoon I am sure Dickon will
come." The long warm rain had done strange things to the herbaceous beds which
bordered the walk by the lower wall. There were things wi sprouting and
pushing out from the roots of clumps of plants and there were actually here and
there glimpses of royal purple and yellow unfurling among the stems of
crocuses 6 months before Mistress Mary would not have seen how the world was
waking up, but now she missed nothing. When she had reached the place
where the door hid itself under the ivy, she was startled by a curious loud
sound. It was the core core of a crow and
it came from the top of the wall, and when she looked up, there sat a big
glossy plumaged blue black bird, looking down at her very wisely
indeed. She had never seen a crow so close before and he made her a little
nervous, but the next moment he spread his wings and flapped away across the
garden. She hoped he was not going to stay inside and she pushed the door open
wondering if he would. When she got fairly into the garden she saw that he
probably did intend to stay because he had alighted on a dwarf apple tree and
under the Apple Tree was lying a little reddish animal with a bushy tail, and
both of them were watching the stooping body and rust red head of Dickon, who was
kneeling on the grass working hard. Mary flew across the grass to him.
"Oh, Dickon! Dickon!" she cried out. "How could you get here so early! How could you! The
sun has only just got up!" He got up himself, laughing and glowing, and tousled;
his eyes like a bit of the sky hey he
said. "I was up long before him. How could I have stayed AB bed the world's all
fair begun again this morning it has and it's working and humming and scratching
and piping and nest building and breathing out scents, till you've got to
be out on it instead of ly on your back.
When the sun did jump up the mo went mad
for joy and I was in the midst of the heather and I run like mad myself
shouting and singing and I come straight here. I couldn't have stayed away. Why the
garden was lying here waiting Mary put her hands on her chest,
panting, as if she had been running herself. "Oh, Dickon! Dickon!" she said. "I'm so
happy I can scarcely breathe!" Seeing him talking to a stranger,
the little bushy-tailed animal rose from its place under the tree and came to him,
and the rook cing once, flew down from its branch and settled quietly on his
shoulder. "This is the little fox cub," he said, rubbing the little reddish animals
head. "It's named Captain and this here is suot suot he flew across the mo with me
and Captain he runs same as if the hounds had been after him. They both felt
same as I did." Neither of the creatures looked as
if he were the least afraid of Mary. When Dickon began to walk about suot stayed
on his shoulder and Captain trotted quietly close to his side.
"See here!" said Dickon. "See how these has pushed up and these and these and hey
look at these here!" He threw himself upon his knees and Mary went down beside him.
They had come upon a whole clump of crocuses burst into purple and orange
and gold. Mary bent her face down and kissed and kissed
them. "You never kiss a person in that way," she said when she lifted her head.
"Flowers are so different." He looked puzzled but smiled he he said, "I've kissed mother
many a time that way when I come in from the Moore after a day's roaming and she
stood there at the door in the sun looking so glad and
comfortable." They ran from one part of the garden to another and found so many
wonders that they were obliged to remind themselves that they must whisper or speak
low. He showed showed her swelling Leaf buds on rose branches which had seemed
dead. He showed her 10,000 new green points pushing through the
mold They put their eager young noses close to the earth and sniffed its
warmed springtime breathing; they dug and pulled and laughed low with rapture
until Mistress Mary's hair was as tumbled as Dickens and her cheeks were
almost as poppy red as his.
There was every joy on earth in the secret garden that morning, and in the
midst of them came a delight more delightful than all, because it was more
wonderful. Swiftly something flew across the wall and darted through the trees to
a close grown corner, a little flare of red breasted bird with something hanging from its
beak Dickens stood quite still and put his hand on Mary almost as if they had
suddenly found themselves l laughing in a church. "We man not stir," he whispered in
broad Yorkshire. "We man not scarce breathe. I knowed he was mate hunting
when I seed him last. It's Ben Weatherstaff's robin. He's building his
nest. He'll stay here if us don't flight him." They settled down softly upon the
grass and sat there without moving. "Us mustn't seem as if us was
watching him too close," said Dickon. "He'd be out with us for good if he got the
notion us was interfering now. He'll be a good bit different till all this is over.
He's setting up housekeeping He'll be shyer and readier to take things ill.
He's got no time for visiting and gossiping Us must keep still a bit and
try to look as if us was grass and trees and bushes. Then when he's got used to
seeing us I'll chirp a bit and he'll know us s will not be in his way."
Mistress Mary was not at all sure that she knew, as Dickens seemed to, how to try
to look like grass and trees and bushes. But he had said the queer thing
as if it were the simplest and most natural thing in the world, and she felt
it must be quite easy to him, and indeed she watched him for a few minutes
carefully, wondering if it was possible for him to quietly turn green and put out branches and
leaves. But he only sat wonderfully still, and when he spoke dropped his voice to
such a softness that it was curious that she could hear him, but she
could. "It's part of the springtime, this nest building is," he said. "I warrant it's
been going on in the same way every year since the world was begun. They've got
their way of thinking and doing things and a body had better not meddle. You can
lose a friend in springtime easier than any other season if you're too
curious." "If we talk about him I can't help looking at him," Mary said as softly
as possible. "We must talk of something else. There is something I want to tell
you." "He'll like it better if us talks to something else," said Dickon. "What is it
that's got to tell me?" "Well— —do you know about calling she
whispered. He turned his head to look at her. "What does that know about him?" he
asked. "I've seen him. I have been to talk to him every day this week. He wants me
to come. He says I'm making him forget about being ill and dying," answered
Mary. Dickon looked actually relieved as soon as the surprise died away from his
round face. "I am glad of that," he exclaimed. "I'm right down glad. It makes
me easier. I know I must say nothing about him and I don't like having to hide
things." "Don't you like hiding the garden?"
said Mary. "I'll never tell about it," he answered. "But I says to mother, 'Mother,' I
says, 'I got a secret to keep. It's not a Baden that knows that. It's no worse than
hiding where a bird's nest is that doesn't mind it, does that Mary always wanted to hear about
mother. "What did she say?" she asked, not at all afraid to hear. Dickon grinned sweet
tempered It was just like her, what she said," he answered. "She give my head a bit
of a rub and laughed and she says Hey lad that can have all the secrets the
likes. I've know the 12 year'.'" "How did you know about Colin?" asked
Mary. "Everybody has knowed about Mr Craven knowed there was a little lad as
was liked to be a and they knowed Mr cra Craven didn't like him to be talked
about. Folks is sorry for Mr Craven because Mrs. Craven was such a pretty
young lady and they were so fond of each other. Mrs. Medlock stops in our cottage
whenever she goes to thit and she doesn't mind talking to mother before us
children, because she knows us has been brought up to be trusty. How did that
find out about him? Martha was in fine trouble the last time she came home. She
said they'd heard him freten and now was asking questions and she didn't know
what to say." Mary told him her story about the midnight weing of the wind
which had wakened her and about the faint far off sounds of the complaining
voice which had led her down the dark corridors with her candle and had ended
with her opening of the door of the dimly lighted room with the carven for
posted bed in the corner. When she described the small Ivory white face and the strange black
rimmed eyes Dickon shook his head thems just like his mother's eyes, only hers
was always laughing they say," he said.
"They say as Mr. Craven can't bear to see him when he's awake and it's because his
eyes is so like his mother's and yet looks so different in his miserable bit of a
face." "Do you think he wants him to die?"
whispered Mary. "No, but he wish wishes he'd never been born. Mother she says that's the
worst thing on earth for a child. Them as is not wanted scarce ever
thrives Mr Craven he'd buy anything as money could buy for the poor lad but
he'd like to forget as he's on earth. For one thing, he's afraid he'll look at him
someday and find his Gro hunchback." "Colin's so afraid of it
himself that he won't sit up," said Mary. "He says he's always thinking that
if he should feel a lump coming he should go crazy and scream himself to
death." "Eh! he oughtn't to lie there thinking things like that," said Dickon. "No
lad could get well as thought them sort of things." The fox was lying on the grass
close by him looking up to ask for a pat now and then, and Dickon bent down and
rubbed his neck softly and thought a few minutes in silence. Presently he lifted
his head and looked round the garden.
"When first we got in here," he said, "it seemed like everything was gray. Look
round now and tell me if there doesn't see a difference." Mary looked and caught her breath a
little. "Why!" she cried, "the gray wall is changing. It is as if a green mist were
creeping over it. It's almost like a green g veil I said Dickon and it'll be greener
and greener till the grays is all gone.
Can I guess what I was thinking I know it was something nice,"
said Mary eagerly. "I believe it was something about Colin." "I was thinking
that if he was out here he wouldn't be watching for lumps to grow on his back;
he'd be watching for buds to break on the rose bushes and he'd likely be healthier," explained
Dicken I was wondering if us could ever get him in the humor to come out here
and lie under the trees in his carriage."
"I've been wondering that myself. I've thought of it almost every
time I've talked to him," said Mary. "I've wondered if he could keep a secret and
I've wondered if we could bring him here without anyone seeing us. I thought
perhaps you could push his carriage. The doctor said he must have fresh air and
if he wants us to take him out no one dare disobey him. He won't go out for
other people and perhaps they will be glad if he will go out with us. He could
order the gardeners to keep away so they wouldn't find out." Dickon was thinking
very hard as he scratched Captain's back. "It'd be good for him, I'll warrant,"
he said us not be thinking he'd better never been born us be just two children watching a
garden grow and he'd be another. Two lads and a little lass just
looking on at the springtime. I warrant it' be better than doctor's
stuff." "He's been been lying in his room so long and he's always been so afraid
of his back that it has made him queer," said Mary. "He knows a good many things
out of books but he doesn't know anything else. He says he has been too
ill to notice things and he hates going out of doors and hates gardens and
gardeners. But he likes to hear about this garden because it is a secret. I
don't tell him much but he said he wanted to see it."
"Us'll have him out here sometime for sure," said Dickon. "I could push his
carriage well enough. Has that noticed how the robin and his mate has been
working while we've been sitting here?
Look at him perched on that branch wondering where it would be best to put
that twig he's got in his beak." He made one of his low whistling
calls and the robin turned his head and looked at him inquiringly, still holding
his twig Dickens spoke to him as Ben weather staff did, but Dickens told tone
was one of friendly advice where's ever thou put it," he said,
"it'll be all right thou knew how to build thy nest before that came out of
the egg. Get on with thee, lad that's got no time to
lose." "Oh, I do like to hear you talk to him!" Mary said, laughing
delightedly. "Ben weather staff scolds him and makes fun of him, and he hops about
and looks as if he understood every word, and I know he likes it. Ben Weatherstaff
says he is so conceited he would rather have stones thrown at him than not be
noticed." Dickon laughed too and went on talking th knows us won't trouble thee,"
he said to the robin. "Us is near being wild things ourselves. Us is nest
building too, bless thee. Look out thou doesn't tell on
us." And though the robin did not answer, because his beak was occupied, Mary knew
that when he flew away with his twig to his own corner of the garden the
darkness of his duw bright eye meant that he would not tell their secret for the